DAN KLEIN: Now we're going to talk
about a very different class of
methods for solving CSPs called
iterative improvement algorithms.
An iterative improvement algorithm,
rather than building your solution up
one step by one step, we're going to
start with an incorrect solution, and
try to fix it by breaking
up conflicts.
Iterative algorithms are an
instance of local search.
A local search method works typically
with a complete state.
For example in this case, all
variables being assigned.
So here's a mini CSP where you have two
nodes, and they're supposed to be
different colors.
And this is a complete state, in that
all variables are assigned.
It is, however, not a goal state
in the sense that the
constraints are not satisfied.
You won't ever get here with the
methods that we talked about
previously.
But in order to apply an iterative
algorithm, we start with an
assignment, and the assignment might
look like this in that it will have
unsatisfied constraints.
So you take some assignment, it will not
in general be a goal assignment.
The operators now reassign
values of variables.
So for example, we might take the
right variable and change
its value to blue.
And now we have a goal.
So there is no fringe, right?
This is life on the edge.
There is no fall back plan, right?
You've got one complete configuration,
and you're tinkering with it one step
at a time, trying to make it better.
Here's an algorithm.
While this single state you
have no fringe, right?
No backup plan.
While this single state that
you have is not a goal, you
pick a variable, right?
How do you pick a variable?
You randomly select any variable
which is currently conflicted.
And then you pick a new value
for that variable.
And one very effective thing in
practice is the min conflicts
heuristic that says you should choose
a value that violates the fewest
constraints.
In other words, we're going to hill
climb where the function we're
climbing is the total number of
violated constraints here.
So in the case of n-queens, for example
here we see four queens.
The states are going to be complete
assignments where every column has a
queen, and our operators pick a column
and move the queen up or down.
The goal test will be, as
before, are there are no
conflicts between the queens?
And the evaluation that we're
going to use is to look at
the number of attacks.
So let's actually see iterative
improvement in action.
Here we have five queens.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going
to run min conflicts for you.
So what does it say?
Well first, of all this
is not a particularly
typical assignment, right?
And you might think, OK, that's great.
We started with everything in
some reasonable position.
In fact, this is about as bad as it's
going to get for this problem, to
start everything off altogether.
This is very conflicted.
OK, so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to run min conflict.
So I pick some variable,
which is conflicted.
And my random number generator
says row two.
OK, so now what I do is I move this
assignment from the first column to a
minimum column, which in this
case might be here.
All right.
Now I pick another conflicted variable,
and my random number
generator says row four.
I've got multiple choices,
so I'll pick one.
Let's see, this one.
I pick a conflicted variable.
Does not have to be the most
conflicted variable.
Maybe this one.
I move it somewhere.
And then I continue this process.
Maybe I pick this one, I move it here.
Maybe I pick this one,
and I move it here.
And now I'm done.
OK.
So instead of building things up step
by step, we start with a complete
assignment.
And we try to fix problems.
Let's see this in the
map coloring case.
So let's now look at iterative
improvement on this graph.
So what do we see right here?
We see a complete assignment.
Everything's been colored, but there's
all kinds of violations of the map
coloring constraint.
So in orange, we see
all the violations.
So when I click Next, what's going to
happen is some conflicted variable is
going to have its value reassigned.
Right.
So it was that one.
And we do it again, and again,
and again, and again.
And we keep doing this step by step.
And now we're done.
So it can be very effective
in practice.